Italian Risorgimento Collection 1998.0312
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
Italian Risorgimento Collection
1650-1918
1998.0312
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
150.0 Linear feet
Arrangement and Description
Arrangement of broadsides described below, per box.
Scope and Content Note
The Italian Risorgimento Collection is comprised of broadsides, pamphlets, books and periodicals from the period of the unification of Italy, 1789 to 1879, with some documents dating as early as 1650.
Related Material
In addition to the broadsides described in this inventory, books (totaling 600 items) and some pamphlets (60 of 1800 items) from the Italian Risorgimento Collection have been cataloged. Titles and call numbers for individual items are available via the Homer Babbidge Library catalog (HOMER).
Uncataloged items, including periodicals and pamphlets, are listed in a card file housed in the Reading Room at the Dodd Research Center.
As pamphlets from the collection are cataloged, they will continue to be added to the Library catalog (HOMER).
Access
The collection is open and available for research.
Provenance and Acquisition
The collection was assembled through four separate purchases in the early 1970s for the now-defunct Center for Italian Studies at the University of Connecticut.
- Broadsides Collection, 1650-1918; 100.23 Linear feet
  Biography/History
  The period known as the Italian Risorgimento, or Resurgence, spanned from the early nineteenth century until the end of the Italian Unification period, which began in 1861 when a constitutional monarchy was established and ended when Rome was made capital of Italy in 1871. Unification of Italy into a republic was the ultimate goal of the Risorgimento activities, though many deemed the contitutional monarchy a successful end to their struggle. Figures such as Giuseppe Mazzini, Giuseppe Garibaldi, Daniele Manin, Aurelio Saffi, Nicola Fabrizi and Massimo d’Azeglio were prominent within the movement, and they can be found as signatories on many of the documents found within the Broadside Collection. Additionally, the leaders of the various regional governments issued many of the notices and proclamations found here. Dukes Francesco IV and Francesco V of Modena, Duchess Maria Luigia and Duke Carlo II of Parma, Tuscan Grand Dukes Ferdinando III, Leopoldo II, and Ferdinando IV and Savoy Kings Carlo Alberto and Victor Emanuel II are all prominent in the collection. Lastly, the pope played a prominent role in peninsular political activities. Popes Pius VII, Leo XII, Pius VIII, and Gregory XVI all actively resisted the revolutionary uprisings of the first part of the nineteenth century while Pius IX was incredibly active in trying to maintain the integrity of the Papal States during the height of the revolutionary activities and moments of unification. The Risorgimento period was punctuated by years of intense revolutionary activity—1831, 1848, and 1849. It is in these years that there is an increased number of documents in the collection.
  Arrangement and Description
  All of the documents in this collection are ordered chronologically. In most cases, the regions and/or cities from which the documents originate are described, though the documents are not arranged by these various regions and/or cities. Regional inventories include those regions which can be found in each year, though this may include only one document (ie., If Papal States, Modena, and Lombardy are listed, there may only be one document from Lombardy).
  There is a significantly larger number of documents from the years 1831, 1848, and 1849, so these documents are separated into the regions, cities and/or political organizations of their given historical moment. The most common designations include: Papal States, Duchy of Modena, Duchy of Parma, Grand Duchy of Tuscany, Lombardy and Venice. There are also a significant number of documents from provisional governments in Rome, Bologna, Pesaro and Urbino, Senigallia, and Reggio. There is a more limited number of documents from the Kingdom of Piedmont and Sardinia and the Kingdom of the Two Sicilies, though these regions are represented. There are also some foreign documents, mostly from France and Austria. Within each regional designation, the documents are ordered chronologically. While documents from any one year are largely in the same location, very small or very large documents are housed elsewhere. The specific materials found in each box are listed in the scope and content section for that box. Within the box, selections of documents are grouped in the most logical order possible, either by a single year or a range of years. In instances where there are disparate years, all years are indicated on the division tabs as well as in this finding aid.
  Some documents from 1796-1802 (Cisalpine Republic) are dated according the French Republican calendar. This calendar is structured in such as way that each Gregorian year spans two Republican years. Documents that fall into this category are organized by the Republican year/month system if no Gregorian year is given. The Gregorian year is noted on the organizing folder. If both a Republican date and a Gregorian date is given, the document is grouped with the Gregorian calendar documents. For example, documents from 1800 span Republican years VIII and IX.
  There are a number of documents that do not contain any date information. These documents are separated in their designated boxes and are placed with the dated documents to which they seem closest. This placement is based on similarities in content, typeface, paper type, and any marginal notations that may exist.
  Scope and Content Note
  The earliest documents from this collection, from 1650 until the early nineteenth century generally relate to practices of everyday life. The large majority of these documents are legal notices stating rules and regulations for various practices. The most common topics include: sanitation ordinances (mostly related to the spread of both human and animal diseases such as cholera and bovine epizootic influenza), notices regarding acceptable currency and specie exchange rates, governmental organizational changes (newly appointed officials), rules and regulations regarding guild affiliation (who could join, who could not, organization of guilds, when guild affiliation must be declared), criminal activity reports and sentences, and rules and regulations regarding the celebration of Carnival (who could wear masks and when they could be worn, rules for the setting off of fireworks, rules regarding general merriment). There are also many Church documents from these years.
  The documents from 1796 to 1800 relate to the Napoleonic invasion of Italy and the establishment of the Cisalpine Republic in Northern Italy. The regions, or departments, of the Cisalpine Republic included the areas around the following cities: Milan, Cremona, Bergamo, Morbegno, Brescia, Mantua, Modena, Reggio, Bologna, Ferrara, and Forlì. The Cisalpine Republic adopted the French Republican calendar, so many of the documents are dated according to this system. These are indicated within their respective boxes. The content of these documents is similar to that discussed above.
  Of any given year in the collection, the most documents come from the major revolutionary years of 1831, 1848, and 1849. The documents from 1831 contain many notices and proclamations from the provisional government that were formed during the various uprisings, particularly in Bologna, Pesaro and Urbino, Senigallia, and Modena. There are also documents from the short lived United Provinces. 1848 was a major year for revolutions not only in Italy, but throughout Europe. Provisional governments were established in Venice, Milan, Piedmont, and eventually in Rome. The collection contains many news reports, proclamations, and declarations from this year. In 1849, the short lived Roman Republic was established, led by the Triumvirate of Giuseppe Mazzini, Aurelio Saffi, and Carlo Armellini. The Roman Republic spread to and was supported by the governments in other cities, including Bologna, Pesaro, and Urbino. The collection contains documents from all of these cities and speaks to the important and progressive changes instituted by the Republican leaders. After the fall of the Roman Republic in July 1849 there is a drastic decrease in the number of broadsides for that year. Throughout these years there are also a significant number of documents issued by the Pope in the Papal States and well as those issued by the hereditary leaders in various regions (Dukes, Grand Dukes, etc.). Many of these serve as counter measures/arguments to those documents issues by the revolutionary/provisional governments. While many of the documents are official in nature, the collection also contains examples of propaganda-type materials. Short pieces discussing the activities of Mazzini, Garibaldi, and others can be found, as well as short writings by these individuals. “Republican Catechisms” are present, which appear to have been used as a method though which to convey and expand the impact of revolutionary goals. There are also news dispatches from various locations, discussing the movements of revolutionary and non-revolutionary forces.
  The documents from the 1850s return to the style, themes, and structures of those from before the revolutionary period. There also seems to be an effort to quell revolutionary activities and stabilize, if not increase, the power of the Church. There are relatively few documents from the unification period, and most maintain the quotidian themes previously discussed. There are a few documents, however, that speak to the success of the revolutionary goals and the achievements made through past struggles.
  - Broadsides, 1800; 1.7 Linear feet (Box 1)
    Arrangement
    For these years, the documents are in chronological order only. The regions/cities listed are those included in each year, but the documents are not separated by these regions/cities.
    The Cisalpine Republic was the French client republic in Northern Italy that existed from 1797 to 1802. The republic followed the French Republican calendar. The years of this calendar began in September of the Gregorian calendar, thus one Republican year spanned parts of two Gregorian years. This calendar also uses a different month system. For example, Republican Year VI ran from 1797-1798. The months Vendemiare, Brumiare, Frimiare, and Nivôse (days 1-10) are from the first year, and the months Nivôse (day 11 onward), Pluviôse, Ventôse, Germinal, Floreal, Prairial, Messidor, Thermidor, Fructidor are from the second year.
    Dates and Regions Represented:
    1800 – French Republic, Cisalpine Republic, standard calendar
  - Broadsides, 1800; 1.7 Linear feet (Box 2)
    Cisalpine Republic (French Republican Calendar) – Year 8 (1800), Vendemiaire – Pluviôse
    Cisalpine Republic (French Republican Calendar) – Year 9 (1800), Messidor – Fructidor
  - Broadsides, 1801-1807; 1.7 Linear feet (Box 3)
    1801-1807 – French Republic, Kingdom of Italy
  - Broadsides, 1808-1809; 1.7 Linear feet (Box 4)
    1808–1809 – French Republic, Kingdom of Italy
  - Broadsides, 1810-1815; 1.7 Linear feet (Box 5)
    1815 – Papal States, Bologna, Tuscany, Milan, Parma
    1814 – Papal States, Bologna, Tuscany, Milan, Mantua, Modena
    1813 – Bologna, Milan, Ravenna
    1812 – Milan
    1811 – Milan, Bologna
    1810 – Milan
  - Broadsides, 1816-1819; 1.7 Linear feet (Box 6)
    1819 – Papal States, Modena
    1818 – Papal States, Mantua
    1817 – Papal States, Parma, Tuscany
    1816 – Modena, Milan
  - Broadsides, 1812-1867; 0.83 Linear feet (Box 7)
    1861-1867 – Turin, Naples, Florence, Marches
    1860 – House of Savoy, Victor Emanuel II, Eugenio
    1839 – Papal States, Lombardy
    1838 – Papal States
    1833 – Florence, Bologna
    1832 – Papal States, Bologna, Modena
    1829 – Papal States
    1827 – Papal States
    1826 – Modena
    1825 – Papal States, Lombardy
    1823 – Papal States
    1821 – Lombardy, Modena
    1820 – Verona
    1819-1812 – Bologna, Lombardy, Mantua, Milan, Modena
    1816-1845 – State Circulars, Piedmont (Turin)
  - Broadsides, 1820-1826; 1.7 Linear feet (Box 8)
    1820 – Papal States, Modena, Parma
    1821 – Papal States, Modena, Mantova
    1822 – Papal States, Modena
    1823 – Papal States, Lombardy
    1824 – Papal States, Parma, Lombardy, Venice
    1825 – Papal States, Modena, Parma
    1826 – Papal States, Parma, Lombardy
  - Broadsides, 1827-1830; 2.3 Linear feet (Box 9)
    1828 – Papal States, Modena, Parma
    1829 – Papal States, Parma, Mantua, Tuscany
    1830 – Papal States, Parma
  - Broadsides, 1831; 1.7 Linear feet (Box 10)
    Within this box the documents are divided into the regional designations of the time period. In some cases, however, only a city is indicated. They are in chronological order within each region.
    1831 –
    Papal States (including Bologna post provisional government)
    Dates and Locations Unknown
  - Broadsides, 1831; 1.7 Linear feet (Box 11)
    1831-
    Parma
    Forlì
    Cesena
    Reggio
    Perugia
    Pesaro, Urbino, Senigallia (Provisional Government)
    Lombardy
    France (foreign dispatches)
    Modena
    Bologna and United Provinces (Provisional Governments)
  - Broadsides, 1831-1833; 0.83 Linear feet (Box 12)
    Within this box the documents from 1831 are divided into the regional designations of the time period. In some cases, however, only a city is indicated. They are in chronological order within each region.
    Ferrara and Rimini
    Reggio (Provisional government)
    Pesaro and Urbino (Provisional government)
    Bologna (Provisional government)
    Papal States
    1832 – Florence, Bologna
    1833 – Bologna, Papal States, Ancona
  - Broadsides, 1841-1859; 0.83 Linear feet (Box 13)
    1841 – Pesaro, Modena, Ascoli
    1844 – Papal States
    1846 – Papal States, Bologna, Modena, Rome
    1847 – Papal States, Rome, Cesena, Tuscany
    1846/1847 – Miscellaneous, exact date unknown
    1850 – Papal States, Macerata, Rome
    1851 – Papal States, Urbino, Rome, Bologna, Modena
    1852 – Papal States, Rome, Urbino, Macerata
    1853 – Papal States, Macerata
    1854 – Papal States, Rome
    1855 – Rome, Reggio
    1857 – Sardinia
    1858 – Papal States
    1859 – Genoa, Florence, Bologna
  - Broadsides, 1831-1833; 2.3 Linear feet (Box 14)
    United Provinces
    Senigallia
    1832 – Papal States
    1833 – Papal States, Modena, Mantua, Tuscany
  - Broadsides, 1834-1839; 2.42 Linear feet (Box 15)
    1839 – Papal States, Modena, Mantua, Lombardy
    1838 – Papal States, Mantua, Lombardy, Parma
    1837 – Papal States, Modena, Lombardy, Tuscany, Parma
    1836 – Papal States, Parma
    1835 – Papal States, Modena, Mantua, Parma
    1834 – Papal States, Lombardy, Mantua, Tuscany
  - Broadsides, 1840-1847; 2.42 Linear feet (Box 16)
    1840 – Papal States, Venetia (Verona), Modena, Parma
    1841 – Papal States, Modena, Parma, Romagna
    1842 – Papal States, Parma, Romagna, Bologna, Mantua
    1843 – Papal States, Parma, Bologna
    1844 – Papal States, Modena, Mantua
    1845 – Papal States, Tuscany, Modena, Two Sicilies, Parma, Lombardy
    1846 – Papal States, Modena, Lombardy, Bologna
    1847 – Papal States, Modena, Lombardy, Mantua, Tuscany
  - Broadsides, 1848; 1.7 Linear feet (Box 17)
    1848 –
    Tuscany
    Duchy of Modena
    Romagna (Bologna)
    Venetia
    Kingdom of Piedmont and Sardinia
    Kingdom of the Two Sicilies
  - Broadsides, 1848-1849; 1.7 Linear feet (Box 18)
    Unknown /Multiple/Other European Origin
    Duchy of Parma
    1849 – Kingdom of the Two Sicilies
    Unknown/Multiple/Other European Origin
    Specific Dates and Locations unknown
  - Broadsides, 1849; 1.7 Linear feet (Box 19)
    1849 – Tuscany
    Provisional Governments in the Marches
    Bologna (Roman Republic and Provisional Governments)
    Mantua
  - Broadsides, 1849; 1.7 Linear feet (Box 20)
    1849 –
    Papal States (Papal Government)
    Roman Republic and Provisional Governments
  - Broadsides, 1848-1849; 0.83 Linear feet (Box 21)
    Papal States Miscellaneous Papal related documents, including Pius IX’s exile in Gaeta
    1848/1849 –
    Date Unknown, various locations/location unknown
  - Broadsides, 1849; 0.83 Linear feet (Box 22)
    Macerata (post Roman Republic)
    Lombardy (Pavia)
  - Broadsides, 1843-1849; 2.71 Linear feet (Box 23)
    Within this box the documents from 1848 and 1849 are divided into the regional designations of the time period. In some cases, however, only a city is indicated. They are in chronological order within each region.
    1848 – Duchy of Modena
    1849 – Lombardy
    1843, 1844, 1846, 1847 – Papal States, Modena
  - Broadsides, 1753-1918; 2.71 Linear feet (Box 24)
    1753-1809 - Modena, Pesaro, Rome
    1850 – Papal States, Modena
    1851 – Lombardy
    1852 - Ancona
    1854 – Lombardy, Modena
    1856 – Modena
    1859 – Volterra
    1860 – Mantua, Pisa, Florence
    1861 – Rome, Spoleto, Cremona, Venice, Pergola, Lucca, Naples
    1862 – Turin, Ravenna, Venice, Ascoli, Rome, Cremona
    1863 – Pesaro
    1864 – Rome
    1865 – Rome, Mantua, Venice
    1866 – Turin, Florence, Venice, Verona
    1867 – Reggio, Florence, Verona, Milan
    1868 – Pesaro
    1870 – Mantua, Bologna, Volterra
    1871 – Rome, Florence
    1872 – Milan
    1878 – Reggio
    1902 – Ravenna
    1904 – Mantua
    1918 – Milan
  - Broadsides, 1850-1852; 2.42 Linear feet (Box 25)
    1850 – Papal States (Rome, Ancona), Tuscany (Florence, Livorno), Lombardy (Milan), Mantua, Bologna
    1851 – Papal States (Rome, Ancona, Macerata, Sinigallia), Lombardy (Milan), Modena, Mantua, Verona
    1852 – Papal States (Rome, Ancona), Modena, Venice, Mantua, Bologna, Forlì
  - Broadsides, 1853-1859; 2.42 Linear feet (Box 26)
    1853 – Papal States, Modena, Mantua, Lombardy
    1854 – Papal States, Modena, Mantua, Bologna, Provisional Government of Cesena
    1855 – Papal States, Mantua, Bologna, Forlì, Lombardy (Milan, Brescia) 1856 – Papal States, Modena, Tuscany, Mantua, Bologna
    1857 – Papal States, Parma, Mantua
    1858 – Papal States, Parma, Mantua, Lombardy
    1859 – Papal States, Tuscany, Bologna, Forlì
    1860 - Rome, Bologna, Turin, Naples
    1861/1862 - Unification Materials
    1860s - Milan, Italian Nation (Dates unknown)
  - Broadsides, 1830-1860; 2.3 Linear feet (Box 27)
    1840s/1850s Dates Unknown -
    Venice
    Piedmont
    Other European Location
    Location unknown
    Election lists (1848/1849)
    Early 1940s, before Pope Pius IX, Dates and Locations unknown
    These documents do not contain dates. Some contain locations. They are organized accorded to presumed date range, though this may have some variation.
  - Broadsides, 1799; 2.3 Linear feet (Folder 1)
    1799 - Cisalpine Republic
  - Broadsides, 1799; 2.3 Linear feet (Folder 2)
    Cisalpine Republic (French Republican Calendar) – Year 7 (1799), Nivôse – Messidor
  - Broadsides, 1798; 2.3 Linear feet (Folder 3)
    1798 - Cisalpine Republic
  - Broadsides, 1798; 2.3 Linear feet (Folder 4)
    Cisalpine Republic (French Republican Calendar) – Year 7 (1798), Vendemiaire – Nivôse
  - Broadsides, 1797; 2.3 Linear feet (Folder 5)
    1797 - Cisalpine Republic
  - Broadsides, 1796; 2.3 Linear feet (Folder 6)
    1796 - Milan, Modena, Rome, Reggio, Bologna
  - Broadsides, 1770-1775; 2.3 Linear feet (Folder 7)
    1795
    1794
    1793
    1792
    1791
    1790
    1789-1786 - Rome, Bergamo, Parma
    1784-1780 - Milan, Florence, Modena
    1779-1777 - Rome, Pesaro, Modena
    1775-1770 - Casale, Modena, Milan, Mantua
  - Broadsides, 1752-1767; 2.3 Linear feet (Folder 8)
    1769-1767 - Modena, Pesaro
    1765-1760 - Modena, Rome, Mantua, Pesaro
    1759-1752 - Mantua, Florence, Venice, Naples, Milan, Urbino, Ferrara
  - Broadsides, 1702-1749; 2.3 Linear feet (Folder 9)
    1749, 1746 - Florence
    1739, 1737, 1736, 1733, 1731 - Florence, Rome, Brescia, Venice
    1724, 1716, 1713, 1712 - Fiesole
    1709, 1707, 1704-1702 - Florence, Urbino
  - Broadsides, 1840-1882; 3.83 Linear feet (Folder 11)
    1840, 1841, 1842, 1843, 1844, 1846, 1847 – Papal States, Parma
    1850 – Lombardy
    1852-1854, 1858 – Papal States
    1859 – Pesaro
    1864 – Ascoli-Piceno
    1879 – Mantua
    1882 – Mantua
  - Broadsides, 1848-1849; 3.83 Linear feet (Folder 12)
    Within this folder the documents are divided into the regional designations of the time period. In some cases, however, only a city is indicated. They are in chronological order within each region.
  - Broadsides, 1831; 3.83 Linear feet (Folder 13)
  - Broadsides, 1832-1839; 3.83 Linear feet (Folder 14)
    1832 – Modena
    1835 – Parma, Papal States, Modena
    1836 – Modena
    1837-1839 – Papal States, Parma
  - Broadsides, 1787-1819; 3.83 Linear feet (Folder 15)
    1809-1787
    1819-1814
  - Broadsides, 1821-1830; 3.83 Linear feet (Folder 16)
    1821, 1822, 1824, 1826, 1828-1830 – Papal States, Parma
  - Broadsides, 1650-1699; 2.3 Linear feet (Folder 10)
    1699, 1698, 1696, 1695, 1665, 1661, 1658, 1650 - Florence, Parma, Brescia, Milan